it came up that you mentioned Young's
attitude towards psychedelics was overly
I think restrictive I think he had you
know he wrote some famous letters I've
actually released some videos on this
channel a video on this channel that's
been watched over a hundred thousand
times regarding what Jung said about
psychedelics it was something that
caught on and people are very interested
in it and you read those comments and
some people you know resonate with the
wisdom of the words and other people
like young and really missing missing
the point here and of course he was
writing before there had been of Gordon
not even the psychedelic Renaissance
even the actual the the sixties
themselves or at least we couldn't see
them in in hindsight things were still
in development and he talks about
mescaline and what-have-you and while
his view I think is fairly too
restrictive and although from also from
the anthropological sense as you as you
mentioned there is a sense that the one
of the key issues he speaks to is the
importance of well if you're going to
sort of touch the sphere where the paint
is made as he turns it if you're going
to take this rocket ship to some of this
material then there's a certain amount
of responsibility in terms of you better
be prepared to have to really integrate
this in a way that's not going to be
destructive of you fundamentally and
right as we as we've mentioned this this
integration is something that yes of
course takes place within and we can do
inner work and in a practice but this
also takes place in relationship and in
relationships of context and part of the
issue was with the sixties is that well
yeah we can say certain things about
Timothy Leary and then and sort of an
inappropriate kind of crack down as
motivated by whether economic reasons
like stupid political reason like a
whole bunch of stuff there's still a
sense in which we were as a culture sort
of quite cut off from an integration
with those traditions of our history
which could be though
context which could help ground the kind
of appropriate integration of this
material and so mm-hmm sure having a
kind of spiritual traditionalist
framework the sort of ritual and you
know often maybe shamanistic but sort of
the initiation framework and cultural
containment that comes with traditional
practice yes yes yeah and I'd like to
sort of presents that the the frame of
that as in this house party you
mentioned there's a certain like that
the moment we find ourselves in is one
that I think opens itself to a lot of
there's a clearing there's a lot of
available energy there's this important
need to to integrate that which has been
broken apart and there's a kind of Wild
West nurse to some structures that that
may come may form now we have loads of
wisdom traditions the lessons in the 60s
in a way right well I mean in some ways
as you alluded to there was more
conventional structure but as regards
this stuff the 60s had an extremely Wild
West kind of approach right I mean
that's that and that was the kind of
critique of the the D contextualization
and the dis embeddedness of psychedelics
in that period right not respecting I
mean you know that a notion of set and
setting but like there already was set
in setting that was back there it's just
like you have to ask you know the mass
attack or something what they were doing
with the mushrooms yeah but I agree with
you there's a lot of available energy
and it's it's extremely open yeah yes
yeah I I hear you on that so an
interesting question I have for you is
and maybe it might be worthwhile to
speak to alchemy a little bit and the
kind of mystery that alchemy is shrouded
in and of course Young took a great
interest in alchemy I myself have found
such incredibly helpful and instrumental
and continually
right possibilities but found in the
phrase solve a at coagula which of
course maps so well on to you know how
we could think from a cognitive science
perspective and so there's the alchemy
piece and then there's the shroud of
mystery of that I'm interested in the
relationship between young and mystery
societies and I'm also interested in
that frame being something that can be
helpful II brought into this and ongoing
conversations which can help us
understand how to appropriately relate
to mystery now right and what the so
yeah I'll stop there yeah yeah yeah so I
think that actually does really usefully
tie together and for the psychedelics to
I mean you know when we talk about there
having you know having an appropriate
cultural context in which can sort of
interpret one's you know spiritual and
initiatory and psychedelic experiences
it's true that having something to do
that is highly effective right having
something that allows you to to construe
what's happening to you and and a way of
making use of it and so on and so forth
right but the tendency very often for
people that make that critique I think
is to then lapse into a kind of you know
sort of retro of shamanism right it's
like what we have to do is is go back to
the original indigenous model now that's
not to say that the original indigenous
model isn't a good one right it might be
highly effective but like at some point
somebody made that up right like it's an
experimental process that somebody made
up some humans made up or you know I
guess if you have a if you have a
different sort of metaphysical frame
maybe it was delivered to them by by
being or beings but the point is like at
some point they didn't have it you know
at some point some humans got into
Mexico and the ate mushrooms for the
first time and when they did they
started figuring out what the hell they
were going to do with what was hitting
them right there was a real time
experimental interpretation that means
that we should
ignore the practical wisdoms of the
humans that have come before us they
weren't stupid right they just didn't
know some things that we know in the way
that we don't know some things that they
knew right we have a different base of
knowledge but the fact is they weren't
dumb humans are smart they do smart
things and they do effective things
which is one of the reasons why I'm so I
really like to thump the pulpit about
magic because it reasons me off when
people treat magic like it's a bunch of
superstitious Buncombe and they don't
understand that what it is is a highly
honed sophisticated set of psycho
technologies that have been developed
around the globe for millennia right in
order to do certain things and we ignore
it at our peril but anyway okay so these
the indigenous practices around this
stuff were tinkered with they were
experimented but they're modeled like
that's how we develop things
correspondingly right we can draw useful
insights from that but that doesn't
necessarily mean if we stop there now
the Western ethos a lot of a time
unfortunately around these things is
what I like to call a fast food atom
bomb ethos right so in the Andes they
chew coca leaves by the quitter have tea
and it invigorates them and a combats or
altitude sickness and whatever right and
that's good but no we concentrate it
down to a white powder and then further
turning into smokeable rocks like we
love reducing things to their poisonous
essence and then consuming them that
fast food is the same gig it's like we
took food which is good for you and
concentrated into a thing that tastes
better than food and it's more
nutritious than food and is vastly
deadlier than food right we saw the
Bliss point as they call them in the
food industry right so we love doing
that kind of stuff that's kind of that's
the core of the instrumental
technological impulse in sort of the
Western ethos and that run out of
control within the framework of
initiation of spiritual advancement is
going to be a problem that's kind of
sometimes how it gets and you get hints
of that in sort of the Silicon Valley
micro dosing culture which is you know
the joke right and it's it's not a fair
caricature in some ways but like in the
sixties it was
turn on tune in drop out right leave
society and now it's like take small
doses of lxd to increase your
productivity coding for Microsoft or
whatever you know so there are lessons
to be pulled from the original context
that's what I'm getting at but that
doesn't mean that innovation stops there
it means that we respect those models
and then we innovate and we combine them
which is what humans do and what we have
always done and that's especially so
when you consider that like it's all
well and good to go and consult
indigenous models for you know ayahuasca
or for you know psilocybin mushrooms
right but what about LSD it doesn't
exist in nature does that mean we can't
have a relationship with it does it mean
that it's not a useful tool do we just
use the same tools since we would use
for a natural component like the answer
is we have to make it up and we have to
make it up based on what we already know
and some good inferences and an
experimental mindset right we have to
kind of experiment and make it up and
the reason that I bring this up within
the alchemical framework is that one of
the things that I love most about
alchemy as a kind of counterculture
expression of spirituality within the
whole period in which it's operating
because it's always it's never the
dominant right alchemy as always
hermetic could tell the sidelines it's
always Gnostic it's always the weirdo
spirituality but it's also deeply deeply
experimental intrinsically inherently
and not that you you don't discover the
alchemists secret recipe and then follow
all the steps right that's amateur
cooking is following the recipe cooking
is about learning what the components of
the operations are